okay we're gonna do meditation but first
I would like to welcome some guests
starting yesterday we're having meetings
with two guys who are very famous for
rebuilding forests and water
conservation and things like that there
used to be forests here and when the
railroad came which is now highway 10 it
was all cut down it's like the way we
are using up all the oil so next
generation won't have any those guys
hundred years ago I didn't think we
would like to have some trees also so
I'd like to welcome albert gates bate
Albert Bates and Greg Ramsey
and I'd like to thank Pocheon power for
bringing him
I was in Sri Lanka once and there's a
beautiful Arboretum it's a whole
mountain covered with beautiful trees
and some of them are hundreds of feet
high and there's a small monks cottage
in the middle they let me stay there and
there's a photo of the people 150 years
ago planting the trees and they knew
they wouldn't see the trees when they
were grown but they built they put them
in for the next generation right and I
think that's cool so let's do that okay
all right we're gonna meditate so Buddha
said what turn off your cell phone
and do your coughing and blow your nose
and I'm not going to explain the
meditation you've been doing it for most
of you four to three weeks now and we'll
just I'll just give you a reminder the
next step okay so these are the first
two parts of the Lyons dance singer
vision be done and then when you come
back in the spring we'll do the third
part okay
it's like those TV shows where you have
to see the second half tomorrow the
advertisers like it all right here we go
it'll be about half an hour so in this
meditation we are using noises in the
room to start the meditation instead of
waiting for the noises to stop
use the sound of the air-conditioner or
crickets or traffic or children and glue
your mind to this sound
you
and please come to the sound of your
heart or the feeling of your heart
beating in your chest
you
then compared to them it would be
quieter if we could actually imagine
ourselves inside of our heart and the
hardest beating around us
you
and it would be more quiet than if we
could step away from the heart and let
it beat by itself
without any interference from us so it's
almost as if the heart is beating far
away in the dark we're not really there
you
and then we try to focus the thoughts in
a quieter place by imagining that our
mind is moving into a single grain of
sugar
landed in the dark and there's a white
beautiful grain of sugar and we slip our
mind in son
you
now imagine the - a vast lake surface of
a lake
with no shorts and will drop a pebble in
the middle of the night and follow
ripples away endlessly so don't let the
ripple stop don't get distracted follow
on a horizontal plane the ripples left
and right from the center of your mind
okay drop the demo
you
then come back to the middle of your
mind
turning on a small light in the middle
of the mine
and clear light flies away from the
center in a sphere
and it stretches on and on and on it
passes through this earth passes this
Sun these planets and expands far into
the outer space the universe continually
expanding clear light of consciousness
the center of your mind
okay turn on the light
you
it would be more quiet to just turn off
the mind no feelings
thoughts no memories so when I say go
then try to imagine your mind has just
shut down completely
no nothing moving through the mine total
silence
something comes up then try to quiet it
push it away stop it
you
compared to that quiet it would be
quiet
I'd turn my mind
and not try to stop thoughts from coming
coming through my mind just
let them come let them go not attached
to them it would be more silent
if I didn't have to make the effort to
try to block them so turn off the mind
and then happily relaxed surrender
two thoughts moving through the mine
don't touch to them
you
so all of that was the preparation
meditation it's just like stretching
your muscles before you run a race
those meditations don't uplift you they
don't
stop the forces that
sample are making us grow older
that cause conflict in the world they're
peaceful but they're not some kind of
solution to the problems of the world so
traditional we go to a ninth
and in this level first we have to
imagine someone sitting in front of us
and its traditional to take
a teacher of some kind so it could be
your mother or father someone who taught
you a lot could be a school teacher
could be even a sports teacher that you
were close to him or someone who taught
you your occupation it could be a
spiritual figure in your life it could
be an historical spiritual figure like
Jesus or Muhammad Moses Buddha but bring
to mind one of the teachers who has
influenced you could be your heart Lama
the one who helped you the most in this
life if you haven't met them it could be
some ideal heart Lama that you would
like to meet in the future and just
bring them to mine in a relaxed way they
are sitting in front of you
they are also relaxed they are looking
at you with love and tenderness and with
your eyes closed you are also looking at
them and make sure they're alive
their heart is beating there
chest is moving with their breath you
can feel the warmth and fragrance of a
human being and it's traditional to at
this point in the meditation you pick
some quality about them that you admire
could be something they taught you or
something you'd like to learn from them
so take a few minutes and try to focus
on one good quality that day impressed
here and that you admire
you
and now go to the center of your mind
for me it's like a center of a room at
night and it's dark and in the very
center of the mind imagine a small nest
bird's nest eggs silver eggs very very
beautiful color and one of them craps
open and out of the egg comes like an
image made of light like a hologram and
it's that quality that you see in your
teacher and that quality drifts towards
the front of your mind like spirit or
something made of light and it leaves
your head for head and then it settles
on top of your teacher and then
appreciate how that quality has come out
of those seeds and left your head and
settled on your teacher and then there
should at this stage there should be a a
feeling a strong feeling that oh I what
I see the goodness I see in my teacher
is actually coming from this deep
seeds inside my own mind and reflect on
that for a little moment and then come
back to the bird's nest and watch a
second silver seat open and a similar
image of light comes out passes through
the front of your head settles on this
teacher and appreciate how it's coming
from you and then go back to the eggs
and see a stream of images coming out
and creating this quality that you see
and your teacher these seeds are opening
at the rate of 65 per second in real
life and it's so fast we can't see it
but in this meditation we are imagining
that we can see it and then practicing
that helps us one day during meditation
to actually see those seeds opening
could even be standing in the kitchen
one day you suddenly observe that you
are creating a pot of water on the stove
or it's coming out of seeds in your own
mind so watch the seeds open in a
relaxed way one by one very beautiful
images coming around very sweet feeling
and this kind of surprise that what you
see is coming from you
now a fun part we go on a little
adventure to try to imagine how we might
have planted those seeds you know past
life so most of us including me I can't
I can't
anytime I want to just look at my past
life I don't have that strength of
meditation but I can we can all imagine
an imaginary past life we can all
fantasize about what we might have done
who we might have been where we might
have lived in some time hundred years
ago or a thousand years ago and we can
make up a story about how we planted
those seeds that are opening here in
2017 into our teacher so go ahead use
your imagination use the images and
impressions of your own life whatever
comes up in your mind incorporate it
into this painting of your imaginary
personal in which you showed kindness to
others and planted these beautiful seeds
to see what you see today
don't let the story stall keep it going
make it more and more interesting and
don't feel restrained let your
imagination run wild anything you can
imagine
is also coming from your past seeds
you've earned them
you deserve those images so use them
now come back to this teacher in front
of you and respectfully ask them to move
to the sign and replace them with
another teacher who looks exactly the
same but this one is like a shell of a
real person this is only an imaginary
teacher because this one doesn't come
from you this one doesn't come from your
seeds and this is how we see everything
around us we don't remember that it's
coming from us from how we treated other
people and we have this automatic
feeling that this person is coming from
their own side and what they say or what
they do to me it's coming from their
side from what they decide to do and
it's not really my fault and the
implication of that is that all the
people we've met in our life it was as
science says an accident there was a
huge explosion and billions of years ago
in the dark and then with no cause and
then little pieces are matter started
moving out from the center some of them
joined together and created elements and
then after almost uncountable years they
became stars planets and then on some
very lucky planets water formed and life
began and evolve until humans came and
then many years later I was born into
this world by accident and my teacher
was born in the same place and then by
accident by by the same forces that
created the earth and planets the same
random forces we met each other by
accident happy accident by accident and
there's not any history between us other
than that there are no past Alliance we
didn't know each other before and after
I die or they die we'll be separated and
there's no destiny that ties us together
life is a huge accident that started
with an explosion and although I love
them and I care for them it's not as
though I created them or they created me
and it's not as though we have any
ultimate purpose together we will be
separated by the same forces that
brought us together by accident so
imagine this
we call false image of a teacher random
teacher accidental meeting and put this
teacher in front of you the real teacher
is all to the side that come from how
you treated other people and now this
fake teacher is sitting in front of you
and try to feel some kind of outrage or
objection
deep in your heart that I don't really
believe in accidents I don't believe
that I don't have any destiny with this
person I don't believe we came from a
random explosion I don't believe we will
be separated with no purpose in our
meeting so at this point in the
meditation which is the most important
part we banish that image we cancel that
image of a accidental meeting and that
leads to some kind of space or some kind
of absence where they used to be but we
cancelled them we said oh you don't
exist and now there's an available space
in front of us and we're supposed to try
to
linked up with this space in some way
become that space let your mind be
filled with this space which is left
over when an Occidental world is
canceled or pushed away and this is
really the available space that all
things can exist in which are coming
from us it's like a blank movie screen
so sit for a minute with the blank movie
screen the absence of accidental life
teacher
for me when I get to this stage there's
their absence in the middle I like to
think of a peach fruit and I took out
the pit the seed in the middle and
there's a little cavity cave where the
seed was and that's the emptiness of any
accidental things but surrounding that
space is this very sweet fruit of all
the people and things I've created by
being kind to others the whole support
system of my life the whole physical
world of blue sky earth beautiful
creatures and people are like the peach
fruit and those are real and they are
coming from my past kindness in the
center there is an empty space where
there's no accidents
then bring the real teacher back into
that space the one that's coming from
your past kindnesses appreciate that
they can only exist in a world which is
not accidental
and then let's come down through the
eight preparation levels first imagine
the mind is turned off and there's no
resistance to thoughts coming through
and then move to a little bit louder
place where you were turned off your
mind but you are fighting images that
come up random the thoughts that come up
you're trying to keep the mind turned
off and that's a little noisier
bring back that clear light from the
edges of space in a sphere contracting
towards you towards the center of your
mind the light is your own awareness now
coming towards the center
bring the ripples back across the lake
endlessly towards the center
slip back into the grain of sugar
see your heart beating from a distance
come back inside the heart and beat with
the heart
and then come back into your body
meditating in this room and watch your
chest beating heart beating
the last step is always to protect these
karma that we just created by putting it
in the bank of other people so we will
give away the good karma of this
meditation by taking three deep exhales
imagine the breath is the golden light
be super relaxed and as the breath flows
out imagine that it's a beautiful light
which is touching people in this room in
this country in this world and bringing
them some happiness and comfort
then gently open your eyes take a
stretch drink something
bachchi make sure our guests have water
okay
I'll take about 10 minutes of questions
then we'll take a break
okay we'll stretch so if there are any
questions you guys did very well I'm
really it felt very very good in here
and I think you did a serious retreat
more serious than I do so thank you for
them it feels really good in the room
and I'm really grateful to rob and all
the other diamond mountain people for
making it possible for us to be here
okay question thank you gaseous oxygen
thank you for bringing us all together
this has been amazing also thank you for
the peach metaphor it relates to a
question I've had for the past month
which is in the ninth level when we drop
the booboo llama it's not coming from
our seeds sometimes I run into this fear
of going into the void like I'm not sure
if I'm doing it right and I was
wondering if you had other tips for how
to slide the mine into emptiness yeah
good so that's the most crucial part of
this song right there your that moment
it took a while to get there right maybe
later and when you do it yourself you
can speed up the first eight levels but
the the the the point in the meditation
which is most important is when you drop
the fake Lama who's not coming from you
and different we have different emotions
at that moment right we feel a little
uncomfortable or we we can understand a
kind of absence but how am I supposed to
relate to that you
supposedly I'm supposed to commune with
that I'm supposed to join
that's when subject and object are
supposed to join together but so how do
I do that you know and I think a safety
net it is important so around you around
that emptiness what I call the peach the
the meet of the peach is this beautiful
world that you're creating and all the
good things in your life
so imagine around that space a kind of
safety which is all the beautiful things
of your life your family your country
your job your the things your body okay
all the things which are coming from you
and then get used to moving into the
empty Center and and then I always like
to tell people it's your problem at that
point you know you're supposed to meld
into that emptiness and lose yourself in
a good way okay and you have to play
with it I think it's something you have
to experience by yourself at someone
David Swensen calls it trying to explain
the taste of an apple to somebody so you
have to play with it you have to have a
few failures you know and then one day
something will click okay
so that's that's a part of the
meditation that I can't describe very
well you have to get into it you have to
dissolve into that emptiness okay and
you have to stay there for as long as
you can and according to Buddhism that's
the antidote to the pain of the world
that moment in the meditation
is the only thing that can stop the pain
of this world not even understanding
that the people around you come from
seeds is enough to stop the pain of the
world you somehow you have to commune
with that emptiness so so so get there
as fast as you can reasonably can and
then stay there the longest okay and you
have to experiment you have to try it it
feels like a rising okay it it feels
like moving up in a elevator it feels
like melding into a higher reality that
doesn't have any colors or shapes or
tangibility and then you lose yourself
and you lose time and you lose awareness
of your own mind and and typically the
first few times you do it directly
it might take 15 20 minutes but you're
not aware of the time okay then you just
come out why do you come out yeah it
takes years to collect the Karma to have
that 20 minutes and the debit card
starts getting deducted the moment you
join with the emptiness it's expensive
karma and then you run out it's why ink
runs out of pens it's why your body gets
all your debit card is deducted every
moment you're in the meditation so then
you have to go back and collect more
good karma what did the first pension
lama say was the best way to collect
that karma yeah like contribute to the
the wisdom okay put buckets of cement
around street signs at retreat centers
you know did something to help other
people okay
contribute to helping other people okay
one more question we'll take a break
Thank You geisha I have a question about
something you said maybe three days ago
a few days ago maybe I misunderstood but
you were saying how in the teachings
impermanence leads to suffering and then
suffering leads to emptiness that last
part I didn't really understand okay
good I thought that and I had the same
problem I thought of a simple way to
explain it which is that this is just a
simple way to explain it so once you're
aware of the impermanence of your body
which in Buddhism means moment by moment
it is dissolving right
two hours spent in a yoga class are two
hours closer to dying and it doesn't
mean you shouldn't do yoga okay
me and Scott are gonna use it as a
reason not to do you
but still you should do your exercise
so that's impermanence and then it's
suffering you know most the loss of
people you love the loss of
relationships the loss of your own body
is suffering and then emptiness is an
understanding that you can do something
about it
you see that's Buddhism so you can
recharge your debit card if you continue
to serve others you make more credit
than you use and in theory you could
become immortal and in theory you could
have the ability to serve many millions
of people okay as time goes on so so
that's how it goes so the step between
suffering and emptiness is that
suffering reminds you suffering pushes
you to to figure out why it's all
happening and what you can do about it
so let's let's say it that way my Lama I
used to say to my Lama you know I I
don't today my motivation doesn't feel
so strong and you know I kind of lost my
way a little bit and he said oh don't
worry suffering will remind you
something will go wrong this week and
you'll be back on track so that's how we
can tie it together I think I have the
suffering that the clock ran out but
let's take a break okay and then we'll
finish the diamond cutter Sutra okay
we're gonna finish up the final verse of
the diamond cutter Sutra we've been
working on it for
two and a half years I think and we're
on the last word which is a broom which
means what clown okay then they said all
the things in your world are similar to
a clone and we were supposed to have six
different I'm sorry
[Music]
yeah seven different meanings okay we
finished the first one which was kind of
subtle and it was that in the future if
you do even tiny Karma's it's possible
you will have clouds in your mind even
at a very high level okay like our heart
okay call traces tres comas okay now run
the second image master Camila Sheila
says about the clown he says remember he
says in my opinion the cloud is talking
about the two kinds of emptiness okay we
had one in the lion stance and that's
that our teacher a human being a living
being is empty of not coming from us
okay in a positive way to say in a
positive way they do come from us in a
negative way they don't not come from us
okay and we always give the example
usually emptiness is most useful when
you're having trouble with somebody okay
like you come home and your husband
yells at you and it looks like you just
opened the door and he's yelling at you
for no reason at all I didn't do
anything I just opened the door okay and
then that's when emptiness is useful for
a human being you have to think oh did I
yell at my kids last week I did and that
planted a karma how does it plant a
karma you listen you hear yourself
yelling at the kids you're always a
witness to everything you ever do
everything you say everything you do
everything you think is recorded by you
okay and then that becomes a seed and
then next week you come home you open
the door
and the seed opens and a luminous image
comes out and it lands on your husband
in a second millisecond and then you see
him yelling at you but you're really
watching one of your own seeds open okay
so master Kamlesh healing when he gets
to the clown he says oh this cloud is
obviously talking about the emptiness of
things and the emptiness of people in
the future when you become a Buddha okay
in the future when you become a Buddha
and at that time the clouds in your mind
will go away
okay the clouds come and they go away
and then you come to your pure mind okay
pure mind means Buddha mine okay what's
Buddha mine okay like what's a Buddha
seen in you what's your Buddha seen okay
like Buddhism says there's a part of you
which has always been a Buddha there's a
partyer which has not been a Buddha okay
the part that yells at your husband is
not a Buddha which part of you is a
Buddha now yeah your emptiness meaning
your your availability your the chance
for you to become an angel it's always
there because you are empty you are like
the boo-boo Lama okay you are always
available your mind is like a blank
screen okay plant the right seeds and
you don't have to see a human arm
anymore you can see a Buddhist arm okay
so you always have that capacity you
always have that availability whether
you use it or not is your problem okay
so so the second meaning of the clouds
is that they will go away okay and the
sky the real sky will appear for Camilla
Sheila the real sky is your Buddha
nature okay your Buddha nature will
it's okay and you'll become a Buddha
okay so for him this guy is a good thing
$10 Amba
he's the pessimist right third meaning
of the clown
he says clouds are another example like
lightening of things that seem to come
into our life just randomly by accident
things you know you're on your way to
Tucson and the car breaks down and it
never broke down before and it just you
don't understand what happened you know
and things come into your life and then
they leave your life and there's no real
trace of them anymore there's a memory
but the things are gone okay so he says
for him the cloud is similar to the
lightning we can't say really where a
cloud came from you can watch the sky
all day and then suddenly there's a
cloud and you don't know where it came
from
and it suddenly it dissolves and it
seems like things come into your life
and leave your life almost at random
with no trace okay that's that's his
first understanding of it we're on
number three right now let's do number
four mm-hmm he says an empty sky cannot
drop the rain but when clouds come the
rain can drop and when the rain drops
the crops grow on the earth okay so the
real nature of the mind is for him he
calls it clear light okay
you had two clear lights in the lion
dance
what are they what's the first one
it's your own consciousness okay and
that's not the meaning of clear light in
Buddhism okay
it's just describes your awareness okay
like I'm aware of Jenny my clear light
is touching her I can see her with my
mind it's like a kind of light okay but
that's not the real meaning of clear
light in Buddhism what's the real
meaning yeah emptiness
so emptiness is a is a word for clear
light okay clear light is a word for
emptiness okay mmm so for him
interpretation number four of the clouds
the mind is really clear light and then
three things can happen in the mind
clouds can come in the mind number one
karma seeds came from yelling at my kids
last week okay
seeds planted by yelling at my kids in
then there's the negative emotion stick
caused me to yell at my kids anger okay
upset okay so we say the world comes
from karma and clashes right comes from
karma and and my negative emotions
okay the world comes from that he adds
another one Ning and Lin yeah go for it
Ming and douche do you yeah subtle
traces of karma okay obvious Karma's
negative emotions and then there's
subtle subtle traces of karma okay
because of those three things clouds can
form in the mind okay or rain can come
okay what's the rain it's your life
what's the cloud your karma your
emotions and your traces what's the sky
the true nature of your mind okay so the
real nature of your mind is clean pure
and then clouds can come anger at your
kids or your husband actions you say
things to them and then small subtle
little feelings that you have to create
subtle Karma's later that by the way do
you remember what the subtle car must do
what's the bad thing that they do those
traces they block come on
link it to the lion stance you can't
stay in that space okay that's what
pushes you out of that space okay subtle
traces he gave a physical example he
gave a verbal example and then he gave a
mental example what was the physical
example among jumping skipping okay
sorry playing rock and roll as a boris
one what's the second one yeah call
someone else like a small bad name like
dork or geek okay not very strong mental
never cause huh what was the cause
though
oh you can say losing your attention
during the association meditation small
subtle things okay small subtle things
okay then that karma pushes you out okay
so for for quite a time you do miss
number four meaning number four yet the
sky is your natural mind empty mine the
clouds are Karma's subtle Karma's
emotions okay
then they cause rain which comes down
and they are the rain sorry
there are the clouds in the rain and
then they grow the problems of your life
okay they grow the problems of your life
cordial Debbie Jimmy wants to go deeper
okay you ready
so there's a school in India called
Sankhya okay Sanka in Tibetan tongue
chamber tongue chimba the name means new
numerators okay and they were strong in
India for a long time they took the yoga
Sutra and messed it up okay
you can read some really confusing books
about Sankhya okay and they have an
interesting idea they say when a rice
grows from a seed rice seed that means
that the rice was in the seed before but
we couldn't see it okay when a seed
grows into a tree this the tree was
always in the scene okay from the
beginning and then at some point that
tree becomes obvious okay but they say
all results are contained in their seeds
before they come out it's kind of a cute
idea okay okay
so all the possible results of a seed
are waiting inside the scene okay and
then when the seed opens they come out
okay that's their idea they have this
idea that the result already exists at
the time of the scene okay
but it's obscured you can't see it it's
inside the seed and you can see it when
it becomes clear we say the seed grew
into a sprout okay that's that's their
idea and he says what the buddha is
trying to say is the results don't exist
in the causes the way people feel they
do okay so whenever there's an ancient
school which is wrong
the ancient school is usually my mind
the reason we teach ancient schools is
because it's an idea that we could have
anytime okay somehow we feel like the
luminous image of my teachers quality
was waiting inside the egg and then it
broke open and the image came out we
feel like that it feels okay to us
somehow the image was waiting then the
mama chicken sat on the egg and it got
warm and then that crack and then the
image which was there came out okay
that's one way that human beings tend to
think of the way things start okay we
think it was waiting and then the seed
opened and the king came out but it was
in the scene okay we feel like that
that's one kind of understanding of
where things come from okay so for coins
oh damn be to me he says the cloud
represents wrong ideas about where
things come from okay we feel like the
crops are somehow already in the seed
and then when the rain comes they come
out but they were always in the scene
okay they were already in the scene then
the rain came and the crop that was
already existing in the scene came out
okay and we feel like that that feels
okay to us okay he says that's a clone
now he gets to the main point okay
number you should be on six I think okay
drat should I go through them all no
five was a cloud that could cause a seed
to open that the tree was already in the
scene five was a cloud that could give
rain that could cause a seed to open and
something that was already in the scene
becomes manifest okay that was that idea
who has that idea
Sonia and me ancient school always means
it's the idea you could have okay now
hmm six is the main one and six is
difficult and six is the whole reason
we're having a class today okay
we had half an hour I'll give you a
seven and let's get it out of the way
cuz sevens easy six is not let's get rid
of number seven okay number seven means
clouds come and go so therefore this
represents impermanence okay that's an
easy one
that's almost free you don't need a
Buddhist commentary to understand that
Buddha mentioned clouds because they
come and go like our life okay it's a
problem with our life your body comes
and goes okay
you don't think so when you're Edmunds
age but when you get to my age you're
like hey wait a minute they say I heard
a joke in China before 40 eat what you
want after 40 pay the doctor my age it's
all like who's who's your heart doctor
who's your liver doctor who's your
kidney doctor who's your urinary doctor
and your doctor you got a night doctor
you don't exchange phone numbers of
girls you exchange phone numbers of
doctors okay
okay number six here's number six six is
subtle
[Music]
when you write something with a pen
right anybody have a pen I can borrow
okay you're faster okay so this let's
say this paper is blank okay and then I
I write something I say hi John okay I
write hi John
on it hi John okay all right
and now here's coins Oh Dembe join me
okay
I'm gonna say something to you it'll
take you about a year to figure it out
okay you ready in a nominal world okay
it's not necessary that causes and
effects have any contact in a nominal
world
it's not necessary that causes and
effects have any contact okay the seed
never meets the tree the water never
touches the seed in a nominal world
nominal means which is coming from my
mind
okay in Buddhism nominal means coming
from my seeds you can call a seed world
seed world if the world is coming from
seeds then the causes never have to
touch the results the pen never touches
the paper and hi John didn't come from
the pen okay in a world which is coming
from seeds
the
and never made contact with the paper
and the words hi John were not caused by
the pen there's no contact between the
pen and the paper and there's no contact
between the pen and the hi John come on
gasps aah
I mean Buddha's whole teaching Buddha's
whole life he was very much like a
scientist he said everything has a cause
everything has a cost dependent
origination okay
nothing happens without a cause okay
don't think your Lama is patient because
your Lamas patient your Lamas patient
cuz you were patient in the past okay
everything has a cause okay everything
has a cost the Buddha spent half his
life saying everything has a cause okay
then he said that cause never touches
the result the cause doesn't cause the
result the gas doesn't make the car go
the gas does nothing because it it can't
okay for a thousand reasons okay it
can't what you think is happening is
impossible okay the whole atomic theory
of the elements is is a huge silly thing
it has no reality it's amazing
everything has a cause Buddha spent half
his life saying that okay then half his
life he said what the cause never
touches the result okay the cat the gas
cannot make the car go okay but gosh la
the gas starts burning just be
for the cargoes yeah this is an old DCI
joke okay we did it in Russia the first
time I remember I was giving a talk and
I start going like this you know then
all these Russians are love bugs I said
why did they ask me why are you doing
that I said what they said you're
banging on the microphone with a pen
stop doing that you know I said I'm
sorry I have to you know and they said
can you just give the talk without
banging on the microphone and I said no
no it's it's almost 12 o'clock I have to
do this you know and they said why I
said I'm making the Sun come up tomorrow
they said what I said this makes the Sun
come up tomorrow why you think that
every day I do it then next day the Sun
comes up I'm afraid if I don't do it
there'll be a problem you know they're
like gage lot just cuz you bang the
microphone today it doesn't make the Sun
come up just try one day don't bang on
the microphone you know let's see if the
Sun comes up tomorrow don't tell me the
car is running because you put gas in it
just before it started running okay got
it you want to drop down to the aspirin
you all go back to the aspirin okay
Connie what makes an aspirin work
she's a nurse what's the active
ingredient most active ingredient cox-2
inhibitor okay it's a chemical that
stops the nerve the the message from
going down the nerve okay so the pain
message can't get to your mind and
that's the active ingredient is it the
active ingredient in an aspirin does it
say that on the label yes
does it work sometimes will you get in
an airplane if you understand okay I
tell this story you know the story you
you you hear there's a new airline
called strong airline you buy a ticket
because they play rock and roll the
whole way and I thought that'd be really
cool
so I buy a ticket and then I go down the
ramp to get on the airplane and there's
a you know flight attendant there with a
pile of papers and she says oh you're
mister oh yeah she said can you just
sign this paper before you get on the
plane and I said you know I was in the
diamond business we don't sign papers
everything in the diamond business is
without contracts we have a verbal code
of ethics and no diamonds are ever
bought and sold with the contracts we
promise and that's enough if you ever
break your promise you cannot get a
diamond from anybody
okay so so I said you know I don't just
sign things let me see it and we have
this fight tug of war you know I'm like
let me see it
she said you don't have to see it it's
okay just sign it I'm like let me see it
you know and then I'm like what is this
and she says it's an insurance waiver so
why do you need an insurance sign an
insurance waiver and she says well we're
a new airline I said I know your new
airline that's why I bought the ticket
because I want to hear rock-and-roll
music the whole flight and she says yeah
and we almost understand how to fly
these planes like we almost got it you
know I said what do you mean almost she
says well most of the
time we land at the other airport safely
I said what do you mean most of the time
she say no sometimes something you know
fall down I said what do you mean
sometimes fall down well we we you know
it's a new airplanes and I'm just son
you know just son I said I'm not gonna
sign this paper are you crazy you know
fall down sometime airplane yeah but we
do that all the time right we take
aspirin and we pay for it and we got
used to believing that Aspen shouldn't
work every time we got used to it we
accept in nobody takes half a bottle
aspirin back to the drugstore and said
give me back half my money only half of
these work to me it's amazing people
don't do that you know that aspen cost
$5 go back say I want two and a half
dollars back they say why you say only
half of them worked okay they say yeah
but only half of them work okay so it's
okay charge me 250 don't sell it for $5
if you know half of them aren't gonna
work okay it means we don't understand
how aspirin works we don't really
understand okay is the active ingredient
active no it's like the song airline
okay it doesn't work it works if
something works sometimes it means
scientists don't understand why it works
okay
what's another sign that aspirin doesn't
work the advertising on TV every year
every year this one really works this
one really works
it means last year's doesn't work when
they say really then you have to say
well you know I don't need it here you
keep it you know I don't need it okay
why are we talking about that well if
your car is full of gasoline will it get
you to Tucson or not we don't know we
don't know there's a what was her name
from Australia New Zealand nest choo she
got in the car full of car gasoline at
Texas Canyon is where those big rocks
are I think she was looking at the big
rocks and she she fell off the oh she
fell asleep probably a class was too
long and she fell off the road she fell
way down her car fell way down went over
and she survived two Mexican and when he
called illegal immigrants were the only
people who would stop and it went down
and got her and she survived okay did
she have a full tank of gas
does it get you to two sons so guess
what are you saying what are you saying
what I'm saying is that sometimes things
happen before other things but that
doesn't mean they caused them okay
geshe-la come on you wrote something on
the paper you asked Janice for a pen
why'd you ask her for a pen if it's not
going to cause hi John okay the pen came
just before hi John
am i right did it cause hi John we say
no Buddhism says no okay
a seed opens at 12:45 and 10 seconds for
pen
at 12:45 in 30 seconds
another seat opens that says hi John
okay but the pen didn't make the hi John
and banging on the microphone didn't
make the Sun come up it looks like that
it looks like that okay if you are weird
enough you will believe that you are
making the Sun come up okay
like you have to be really weird one out
of a billion people but this one one out
of one people they believe they really
believe that this coming from the pen
this coming from the pen okay and the
tree come from the scene they believed
then they really believed then and the
llama come from the image
maybe that seed opening is like banging
on the microphone and maybe that llama
just comes after there does now that's a
long story
can the image actually touch that lover
we're okay
like the image come out of your mind
right like a muddy pasta you know like a
butterfly ginger summer
what do you call in Chinese would ya it
comes down and lands on the llama and
then you see this quality right how can
it touch the llama where does it touch a
llama first is that why gets like got
bald it always land here first
you know where do they touch where does
the image touch the is there a first
piece that touches or not oh it touches
everything at once is there a first
place where it touches okay just a
little bit okay where there's no space
between the two right right the image go
go to the llama and then go poop touch
the llama booboo don't just that's how
how how small is that space just before
they touch is it the smallest space
space that can be just before they touch
it's they're the smallest place that can
be or not yes or no there must be a
smallest place that can be because the
next moment they touch it has to be
think of just think about it forget
Buddhism
image comes to the llama here's my image
here's my llama come closer and close
and then the closest two things can be
and then in the next moment they touch
am i right is is there a closest that
two things can be is it possible is
there such a thing is they're super
close and then touch you feel like that
though you believe that my car got super
close to the other car then they got as
close as possible without touching and
then the rental car hit the other car
now I gotta pay five hundred dollars the
smallest space possible became touching
okay so Buddhism says this is hard okay
this is really hard but you have a long
plane ride you can think about it or you
can sleep or you can watch a movie when
things get really close okay and you say
okay that's as close as they can be
before they touch okay right
that space can you divide it wait how
people say yes have people say no can
you divide it or not then it's not the
closest she's like Lucas like wait let's
do that again
if there are closer space between the
image and the llama but there must be
just before they touch cuz then they
touch what do you mean they never touch
so the llamas not doesn't have good
Connie I knew it they have to touch the
image has to go on the lumber man they
have to touch the after touch if they
don't touch the llama doesn't have
quality
come on anyway it feels like that right
they get closer closer closer closer
closer and then there's a smallest space
possible and you can't split it okay
even with a razor blade you can't split
it okay it's as small as possible and
then they touch but there is no such
space because you can divide any space
okay in the next millaa millaa millaa
millaa ii there's still some space right
so this is not just some philosophy game
this is not some stupid philosophy okay
the goal of Buddhism is to make you
successful and to make you happy right
the goal of Buddhism is to become
successful financially why not and along
with everybody and then what beautiful
relationships and then what healthy body
and then what peaceful mind and then
what whole world no war okay like that
we have goals right we want things to
happen so we're not saying everything
doesn't exist
that that's not true okay if you sit
like this I'm meditating on emptiness
man you know are you gonna go to work no
and because this man
okay it's not the point okay so now I
don't want to go to work why my finger
can't touch the money I mean they get
close and close but you know they never
really touched so why should I go to
work okay what happens when you get some
somebody gave me a red arm look what
happens when you get a random alone
first you don't have a right arm oh okay
then you do have a red home who put the
envelope in my hand my scene okay my
scenes okay it's not possible that the
distance got shorter shoulders you know
[Music]
get the money okay it's not possible
okay so think about it it's not some
stupid philosophy it's not that it's not
that you had a karma to see me pick up a
pen and then you had a karma to see hi
John and they are not connected
occasional one happened before the other
yeah I know I know but it's just an
accident okay got it
there is no cause and effect in the
system of philosophy of the cause and
effect guy called Buddha there's no
cousin effect if you don't like the
movie on the plane on the way home to
Hong Kong whose fault is it penny it's
your father
don't complain to United Airlines all
right if you don't like the ending to
the movie whose father is the ending of
the movie connected to the beginning of
the movie no okay your mind make the
beginning
then your mind make the middle then your
mind make the ending of the movie okay
why is the arts movies so bad nowadays
your mind is bad okay
nothing touches anything else that's the
sixth meaning of the cloud that's the
sixth meaning of the cloud when the rain
comes out of the cloud and touches the
seed and the seed opens and the tree
comes out the water never touched the
scene okay and the sprout the seed never
touch the tree okay they never make
contact there was no contact your mind
created a cloud and then your mind
created water and then your mind created
water touch the scene and then your mind
created the tree come out of the scene
they are not connecting they are not
causing a thing okay the foundation of
reality is not chemicals iron oxygen
hydrogen is none okay
it's not the world is not made of little
balls of things that can't touch each
other okay the world is not made of
little balls of things that cannot touch
each other and the world is not random
and the world didn't come from a big
bang and your llama isn't a big mistake
of too many atoms came here and not
enough atoms here coming from how you
treat other people okay the world it's
only coming from how you treat other
people okay and nothing else
some morality or good behavior kindness
is the real Adams in this world okay
what creates this world is kindness and
not Adams and not ink and not paper okay
it's how you treat other people creates
the foundation of this reality is not
physical it's not atoms because they
cannot exist and they cannot work the
way people think the foundation of
reality is compassion cool that's a good
place to stop okay cloud ok cloud make
rain rain make crops nothing touches the
water never touches the scene that's
number six okay
what makes the world go around is taking
care of each other okay